Sorry, Mark. Sorry, Mark.
Apologize in advance.
I'm holding, you know, dollars on chain
and I'm getting 10% yield. My bank gives
me like half a percent. So, why would I
ever go back to my bank?
You know, all your costs are in
Philippine peso because you're producing
in the Philippines, but now your your
revenue is in Mexican
>> [music]
>> peso, right? And so, what you would want
to do is you would knowing when you get
those future cash flows, you would
basically buy a hedge. Whatever you get,
you know, you pay a small fee for
basically making sure that the money you
get is what you expect. [music] So, the
the product that you would be buying on
chain is a structured product which
basically
having lived through the, you know, 2008
financial crisis,
I worry about that a little bit, right?
Like, real estate all coming on chain
sounds great, but only if there's
a way to do it sort of in a way that
doesn't kind of create another
Armageddon.
I am very happy to be with Rene. He's
the co-founder of Solo.
Such a great chat with you earlier on
stage. Likewise, yeah. It's good to chat
more.
Um you talked about stablecoins a lot
and I think that is a topic that, you
know, a lot of traditional finance
people are just realizing. Why are they
just cut catching up now? Yeah, good
question. I wonder about that.
>> Yeah.
You know, I think the reason why it took
so long, if I if I had to sort of
make a guess, is really because the
all the supporting infrastructure wasn't
quite ready for a regular person to
easily, you know, on-ramp, as we say, so
kind of go from their kind of normal
currency
um either in a bank account or like a,
you know, mobile money account to come
on chain and then also easily go back,
you know, off-ramp, kind of go back into
their local currency
just wasn't something that for, you
know, many years was easy um from a sort
of UX perspective, but then it also
wasn't something that was, you know,
very very cost-efficient, right? So, you
would lose a lot of money coming on
chain and then also off-boarding again.
And I think in 2025, we are finally at a
point where really in most markets
around the world um that's now possible.
It's happening fast, it's easy, you
know, it's something that really regular
people that have not ever used crypto
can do.
Um and I think that's a big reason why
we're we're seeing more mass market
appeal now for stablecoins and sort of
this becoming part of the public
conversation. Um I think another factor
is that there's now in 2025, there's a
lot more interesting application. 5
years ago, what could you really do on
chain? I mean, not not that much, right?
There wasn't really You could send a
token to another person, great. I think
in 2025, we have, you know, prediction
markets going mainstream. Um we have you
know, games that, you know, have token
economies that have pretty big user
bases. We have all kinds of like, you
know, on-chain applications where
people people want to actually use them
and so they have a much bigger sort of
incentive to take that more difficult
step of on-ramping.
>> You don't think it's because of Trump?
He [laughter] He's a big part of this.
>> is a reason. I mean, definitely kind of
created so much awareness and um
yeah, you know, I I agree. I mean, meme
coins, of course, like brought a lot of
people also, right? This is their first
interaction. So, I think actually like
there's a nice nice way of kind of tying
in some of the experiments like meme
coins and NFTs into this journey, right?
Because all of this helped to actually
um
bring people, you know, into a world
where they now have a wallet and they
realize, "Oh wow, I'm I'm holding, you
know, dollars on chain and I'm getting
10% yield. My bank gives me like half a
percent, so why would I ever go back to
my bank, right?" So, I think there's
certainly some of that and I think all
of that helped kind of make stablecoins
sort of explode, as we say this year.
For users, right? Um
meme coins or online gaming, those are
those are a small number of users if you
compare to the world's population. But I
think the legislation and the law in
place actually introduced this to
everybody else that wasn't really
interested in this. It sounds like such
an important topic that governments
should be working on, but
a lot of very conservative governments
are still just
watching, observing.
And my worry is that they're going to be
so far behind. Yeah, I know. And I think
this is sometimes what we what we're
seeing in crypto, right? Like the users
start just start doing stuff and you
know, there's a little bit of maybe even
gray area, right? Where it's not really
clear. How does this fall into existing
laws? But then it becomes so big that in
some cases actually nice. It educates
regulators, right? It gives them a sense
for, oh,
are consumers sufficiently protected,
right? Probably also helps create better
laws, right?
Versus trying to put laws now for
something that may or may not happen in
the future and you know, how
how would you know how people are going
to interact with these stable coins,
right? Now we know because we have like
years of history of seeing that, but I
think to many of us it was clear from
the very get-go that yes, stable coins
are going to be big. And even now I
think you know, like we talked about on
the panel, we're still early innings,
right? We're still still mostly dollar
stable coins.
Um it's still um you know, not much
composability
um beyond sort of some of these initial
kind of use cases.
Um so the best is yet to come, I think,
as it comes to stable coins.
>> So, everyone has that special edge. What
is yours?
>> Mhm.
Yeah, I think it's a good point,
especially in 2025 when you have um so
many more chains like launch, you know,
uh that say, "Hey, we're like this chain
for stable coins, right?" At the end of
the day, I think it's easy to to launch
a chain, really in 2025. Um it's
probably never been easier to launch a
blockchain, but I think what what a lot
of people, even founders, right, that
start blockchains underestimate is the
the kind of infrastructure you have to
build around the blockchain, right? Like
and that's everything from what we
talked about, the on-off ramps, it's
like different sort of
infrastructure, right, that that
projects want to tie in to actually make
this stuff useful. And so, it's one
thing to launch a chain and have a bunch
of like TVL on it, like people just
moving some tokens in, it's another to
actually have the blockchain be used for
economic activity, right? And so, in the
case of the Philippines, um it really
only makes sense if the person that then
kind of receives, you know, that stable
coin in their wallets can do something
with it, right? Can they off-ramp? Can
they use it to pay at a local store? Um
you know, there's There's an example,
recently a friend was uh traveling to to
Kenya, Nairobi,
and um
you know, he was like, "Hey, you go
there a lot. Like, what's what's your
like, what do I need to know?" He was
like, "You know what? Until like maybe a
year ago, I would have said, 'Okay, when
you get to the airport, buy a local SIM
card, get M-Pesa because you'll need
that to pay at all the local stores.' Um
this time I was like, "Look, just use
M-Pesa. You know, use Opera's kind of uh
wallet because you can actually use it
anywhere M-Pesa is accepted. And you
can, you know, have your USDT stablecoin
in it and just pay with that really
anywhere." So, no
like really like it couldn't be easier,
right? And so
>> you to help me visualize how that works.
You said it's on a browser, an app, or
what what is it?
>> Yeah, let's unpack Yeah, sorry. Let's
unpack that a little bit. So, yesterday
here we announced that with Opera we're
basically doubling down on this on this
partnership and it actually it started
in the browser. You're you're you're
you're right. So,
Opera has I think 300 million active
users, has you know, brought hundreds of
millions of people online through their
browsers. Their Android browser is
actually the most popular browser in
Africa.
And so
um, it's so popular because they
subsidize bandwidth. It's also super
lightweight, so it doesn't take a lot
of, you know,
data to kind of download, right? So,
people really love it, right? Makes
makes a lot of sense.
So, they built a wallet directly into
that Android browser.
And after they launched it, it became so
popular and people were like, "Hey, I
want to I want to use this too, but, you
know, I'm not in Africa on an Android
phone."
So, they ended up also launching
standalone Android and iOS
wallets for M-Pesa. So, now really
anyone anywhere can use M-Pesa and and,
you know, use it to send funds or use
any of the the many mini apps in in
M-Pesa. It's becoming
kind of a way for any Opera user,
whether they're on iOS or Android,
right, to to easily have access to a
wallet. So, what you are saying is if I
were to go to Kenya on vacation right
now, I just have to
download? And when I pay the vendors, do
I send stablecoins?
And are they all
sort of So, there's a local provider
that's basically managing the flow so
that the vendor still gets paid as they
would otherwise. But for you as a user,
all you're doing is here you're
effectively paying in in the stable coin
in your wallet. You You set it up, you
have your wallets, um and then you can,
you know,
make payments based on phone numbers, so
you don't even have to deal with like
public keys. Um in the case of like, you
know, M-Pesa in in Kenya, you know, they
have like these kind of short kind of
codes, right? So, that's that's another
way of um of making a payment. Um but
but yeah, it's really it it feels like a
web two application because it abstracts
everything
away that would otherwise be difficult
or get in the way when you're using a
crypto wallet. Um
there's so many stories of people that
now have the ability to, you know, save
in dollars or hold gold or um send money
to, you know, a relative uh in a market
where that's not possible without a big
fee previously. Um and that's, you know,
those are the most rewarding stories.
What were you doing before this? Um so,
I started my career was um actually in
traditional finance. So, I was at Morgan
Stanley, um structuring derivatives. Um
there's a whole another story there
around like stuff that we're not doing
on chain yet, um that I think will
happen in the next um
hopefully 5 years.
>> Since you're talking about it.
>> Uh yeah. You want to dive in? Okay.
>> [laughter]
>> So,
um one of sort of the areas that I
worked on at Morgan Stanley was
basically helping
mostly corporate, some some sovereigns
as well, um with sort of their risk
management. So, you know, like different
interest rates and uh and currencies and
structuring derivatives, you know,
mostly swaps or swap chains to to manage
that risk.
Um and the way it works is, you know,
from a from sort of my perspective, I
was in the structuring desk, I would
think about a product and then I would
call up, you know, the
the the Euro desk, be like, "Hey, give
me a quote on dollar euro, right?" And
then but sometimes for like the more
long-tail currencies, right? Uh thin
markets, right? Like not too many people
are trading Philippine pesos to um
Mexican pesos, for example, right? On a
like this is not a it's not a deep
market. Everything goes through dollars,
right? And so it's it's not that
efficient. And so it really makes sense
if you're setting up like, you know,
products for bigger customers, right?
Where you where you have some, you know,
some ability to kind of structure things
up properly, but you know, we wouldn't
do that kind of work for like a small
business for example, right? It's just
not, you know, it doesn't doesn't make
sense. You know, fast forward many, many
years now, I'm like, "Wow, you know,
there will be a point in time
where you know, the small business can
literally buy this product on chain
permissionless without the need to talk
to a bank. So the the product that you
would be buying on chain is a structured
product,
which basically
based on the movement of
of currencies and interest rates
and does certain payouts. So I'll give
you I'll give an easy example. So you
could be a company in the Philippines
that actually exports some of their
stuff that they're building to to
Mexico, right? And
the company in Mexico is saying, "Hey,
I'm paying you, you know, yes, I'll pay
you once I get the goods, right?" And so
you agree on a price, but during the
time that you deliver the goods and they
pay you, right? The interest that sorry,
the the exchange rate changes and so you
end up, you know, all your costs are in
Filipino peso because you're producing
in the Philippines, but now your your
revenue is in Mexican peso, right? And
so what do you do, right?
And so what you would want to do is you
would knowing when you get those future
flows, you would basically buy a hedge,
right? so that whatever you get, you
know, you pay a small fee for basically
making sure that the money you get is
what you expect. Now this is kind of
usually yeah, a big company just calls
up their their bank and or manages that
kind of that at a portfolio level,
right? Um
but for a small company, yeah, there's
not not really a solution to do that,
right? Um
And so to do that on chain, well, first
of all, we need
Mexican peso, Filipino peso stable
coins. We need stable coins for all
currencies, right?
Right now we only
Right now we mostly have dollar stable
coins, right?
So Celo is actually number one chain for
like
diversity of stable coins. So having
many many different stable coins. So we
actually have a Filipino peso that
people are using. We have Kenyan
shilling. We have a lot of these local
currencies because we see a future
where, you know, people will want to do
that stuff. Um, now the volumes
in these cross currency pools, think
about it as like a Uniswap pool, but
instead of like, you know,
Celo wrapped ETH, it's dollar to Kenyan
shilling on chain, right?
>> But the governments have to come up with
their own stable coin for this to
happen, though.
It could be It could be that or like
with dollar stable coins, it's, you
know, private providers like Tether,
Circle, right? Circle actually uh and
Tether, too, have launched euro stable
coins as well, right? So there are there
already examples of existing stable coin
issuers issuing other stable coins, but
then in many markets you actually have
local providers. Um, in many markets you
have already multiple providers issuing
local stable coins.
Um, and so that that is something that's
been emerging. We've actually from the
Celo side supported a lot of these local
issuers because we want to see more
local stable coin issuance.
Um, there's also
um synthetic um stable coins. So Mento
protocol on Celo is an example of that.
Um, there there others. And and then the
next step is to basically create
liquidity in in the spot markets so that
anyone can easily trade sort of in a
spot market between two currencies.
Um, and then the next step is to
not just do this for spot markets, but
for future for future markets, right?
And
uh we're not we're not there yet. No one
like that's that's not happening
anywhere. I think it's going to happen
in the next few years, right? As people
now there's going to be demand for Oh,
yeah, I want pesos in the future, so
I'm, you know,
I I there's there's on-chain demand for
that. Um so, once we have
basically fully developed yield curves
as a result of these kind of future
markets and liquidity in these future
markets for these different pairs,
um I think we'll have something that
actually will work better than the
traditional financial system because
I think with all the innovation that's
been happening around AMMs in, you know,
with with DeFi in general,
um we can create more capital-efficient
ways of um actually allowing people to
trade between different currencies. And
so, my my prediction is I'm going to put
my stuff, you know, out there that in
like 5 years' time it's going to be
actually cheaper for a business to do
this kind of swap or swap chain that
they traditionally would have called a
big bank for on-chain than, you know,
doing it the traditional way. You are
killing your previous employer. Yeah.
Who would have thought, right? Weird.
>> I know. Sorry, Morgan Stanley.
Apologize in advance. I want to know
your take on real-world asset. What do
you really see happening right now? Uh
I've interviewed a few really important
guests. They were talking about how
T-bills are already on-chain, and I
wonder if that is very
easy for everyday people to have access
to or is it just for the institutions or
companies? A lot of RWAs
exist, but they kind of exist in their
own kind of bubble, right? Not not that
accessible to to mainstream. Um which I
think is a is a big um is a big
opportunity. I think today it's I think
this was also something we talked about
on the panel, right? For the most part
it's just crypto money, on-chain funds
providing additional demand for for
these assets. Think about a world where
all the assets can be transferred. I can
transfer half of my house to you right
now. That is supposed to be the ideal
world, right?
>> Yeah. It sounds like that there'll be a
lot of things trying to stop you or stop
that. Definitely having lived through
the you know, 2008
um
financial crisis,
I worry about that a little bit, right?
Like you imagine people like real estate
all coming on-chain sounds great, but
only if there's
a way to do it sort of in a way that
doesn't kind of create another
Armageddon, right? Where suddenly people
you know, um
take out, you know, or like use it as
other collateral and then, you know,
take out loans against it, leverage
leverage up, and and don't necessarily
understand um
sort of the financial risks that go
hand-in-hand with that. Um so so that is
something that gives me some pause,
right? But look, giving someone
in in the global south access to like
Google or Apple stock, I think that's
totally like overdue, right? And so I
think it's depends a little bit on what
product are we talking what asset are we
talking about um what are maybe the
consumer protections around how it's
used on-chain.
Um
but yeah, I think that's that's for us
to figure out. Last question is maybe
help us imagine this beautiful world in
10 years. How would
the transaction of value look like? 10
years is is a long time.
>> Yeah. Enough time. Yeah. Mhm. I mean,
there's also everything that's been
happening with AI, right? Where
I think probably in 10 years the way we
interact, you know,
is going to change pretty dramatically,
right? So maybe it's no longer an app on
your phone, but you just, you know, like
talk to an LLM and doing stuff on your
behalf, right? That's that's definitely
coming and so I think 10 years from now,
we probably have a large part of
on-chain transactions being agentic or
being agent driven. I I do I do think
we'll probably, you know, just have
something where we speak into some form
of device, right? And we know it's kind
of acting based on some preferences that
you know, the system knows it's what we
kind of want or need, you know, like
that all works seamlessly.
Um but I don't know. 10 years it's yeah,
that's a lot of It's a long time. That's
a lot of time, yeah. And I am super
excited about what could happen. Yeah,
man. Yeah. That's why we're all here.
Thank you so much for this conversation.
Thank you so much.
>> Yeah.